<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="out/encoding_pedagogy_worked_example.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="reading_view_author.css" title="Reading view"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Encoding Pedagogy — Worked Example Passages</title>
        <author>Yashee</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Draft encoding for the DH2026 pilot project "Between Category and Code."
        Not for distribution outside supervisor review.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Patrick Olivelle (trans.), <title>The Early Upanisads</title>.
        Kena Upanishad and Katha Upanishad.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <person xml:id="student"><persName>Student (unnamed)</persName></person>
          <person xml:id="teacher"><persName>Teacher (unnamed)</persName></person>
          <person xml:id="naciketas"><persName>Naciketas</persName></person>
          <person xml:id="death"><persName>Death (Yama)</persName></person>
        </listPerson>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>

      <div type="text" n="Kena Upanishad" xml:id="kena">

        <div type="khanda" n="1">
          <lg type="verse" n="1" ana="#cat-A">
            <l>By whom impelled, by whom compelled, does the mind soar forth?</l>
            <l>By whom enjoined does the breath, march on as the first?</l>
            <l>By whom is this speech impelled, with which people speak?</l>
            <l>And who is the god that joins the sight and hearing?</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="verse" n="2" ana="#cat-K">
            <l>That which is the hearing behind hearing, the thinking behind thinking, the speech
            behind speech, the sight behind sight—</l>
            <l>It is also the breathing behind breathing—</l>
            <l>Freed completely from these, the wise become immortal, when they depart from this
            world.</l>
          </lg>
        </div>

        <div type="khanda" n="4">
          <lg type="verse" n="4">
            <l>Here is its rule of substitution<ptr type="note" target="#fn1"/>: the cry "Ah!" when
            lightning has flashed, the cry "Ah!" when it made them blink—such it is with respect
            to the divine sphere.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="verse" n="5" ana="#cat-G">
            <l>And with respect to the body (atman)—when something here comes to the mind somehow
            and through it the imagination suddenly recollects something.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="verse" n="6" ana="#cat-K">
            <l>Now, its name is Tadvana, and it should be venerated as Tadvana. When someone knows
            it as such, all beings long for him.</l>
          </lg>
          <sp who="#student">
            <speaker>Student</speaker>
            <lg type="verse" n="7" ana="#cat-E">
              <l>"Sir, teach me the hidden connection (upanisad)<ptr type="note" target="#fn2"/>."</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#teacher">
            <speaker>Teacher</speaker>
            <p>"You have been taught the hidden connection (upanisad)—indeed, we have taught you
            the hidden connection (upanisad) relating to brahman itself.</p>
          </sp>
        </div>

      </div>

      <div type="text" n="Katha Upanishad" xml:id="katha">

        <div type="valli" n="1">
          <sp who="#naciketas">
            <speaker>Naciketas</speaker>
            <lg type="verse" n="12" ana="#cat-H">
              <l>In the world of heaven there is no fear;</l>
              <l>there one has no fear of old age or you.</l>
              <l>Transcending both these—both hunger and thirst,</l>
              <l>beyond all sorrows, one rejoices in heaven.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="verse" n="13" ana="#cat-H">
              <l>You, O Death, are studying,</l>
              <l>the fire-altar that leads to heaven;</l>
              <l>Explain that to me, a man who has faith;</l>
              <l>People who are in heaven enjoy the immortal state—</l>
              <l>It is this I choose with my second wish.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#death">
            <speaker>Death</speaker>
            <lg type="verse" n="14" ana="#cat-M">
              <l>I shall explain to you—</l>
              <l>and heed this teaching of mine,</l>
              <l>O Naciketas, you who understand—</l>
              <l>the fire-altar that leads to heaven,</l>
              <l>to the attainment of an endless world,</l>
              <l>and is its very foundation.</l>
              <l>Know that it lies hidden,</l>
              <l>In the cave of the heart.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
        </div>

        <div type="valli" n="2">
          <lg type="verse" n="5" ana="#cat-L">
            <l>Wallowing in ignorance, but calling themselves wise,</l>
            <l>Thinking themselves learned, the fools go around,</l>
            <l>staggering about like a group of blind men,</l>
            <l>led by a man who is himself blind.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="verse" n="11" ana="#cat-H">
            <l>Satisfying desires is the foundation of the world;</l>
            <l>Uninterrupted rites bring ultimate security;</l>
            <l>Great and widespread praise is the foundation—</l>
            <l>these you have seen, wise Naciketas,</l>
            <l>and having seen, firmly rejected.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="verse" n="12" ana="#cat-M">
            <l>The primeval one who is hard to perceive,</l>
            <l>wrapped in mystery, hidden in the cave,</l>
            <l>residing within the impenetrable depth—</l>
            <l>Regarding him as god, an insight</l>
            <l>gained by inner contemplation,</l>
            <l>both sorrow and joy the wise abandon.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="verse" n="13" ana="#cat-G">
            <l>When a mortal has heard it, understood it;</l>
            <l>when he has drawn it out,</l>
            <l>and grasped this subtle point of doctrine;</l>
            <l>He rejoices, for he has found</l>
            <l>something in which he could rejoice.</l>
            <l>To him I consider my house</l>
            <l>to be open, Naciketas.</l>
          </lg>
          <sp who="#naciketas" cert="low">
            <speaker>Naciketas <hi rend="superscript">?</hi></speaker>
            <lg type="verse" n="14" ana="#cat-F">
              <l>Tell me what you see as—</l>
              <l>Different from the right doctrine and from the wrong;</l>
              <l>Different from what's done here and what's left undone;</l>
              <l>Different from what has been and what's yet to be.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
        </div>

        <div type="valli" n="6">
          <!--
            No @ana on this passage by design: initially tested against
            Category A, it held cleanly under G's decision rule instead, but
            per the project's decision not to formally name a sub-category for
            this ladder-like pattern, it carries a tagging-history footnote
            only - no category badge is rendered on the reading view.
          -->
          <lg type="verse" n="7">
            <l>Higher than the senses is the mind;</l>
            <l>Higher than the mind is the essence;</l>
            <l>Higher than the essence is the immense self;</l>
            <l>Higher than the immense is the unmanifest.<ptr type="note" target="#fn3"/></l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="verse" n="8">
            <l>Higher than the unmanifest is the person,</l>
            <l>pervading all and without any marks.</l>
            <l>Knowing him, a man is freed,</l>
            <l>and attains immortality.<ptr type="note" target="#fn3"/></l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="verse" n="9">
            <l>His appearance is beyond the range of sight;</l>
            <l>no one can see him with his sight;</l>
            <l>With the heart, with insight, with thought,</l>
            <l>has he been contemplated—</l>
            <l>Those who know this become immortal.<ptr type="note" target="#fn3"/></l>
          </lg>
        </div>

      </div>

    </body>

    <back>

      <div type="glossary">
        <interpGrp type="pedagogicalCategory">
          
          <interp xml:id="cat-A" n="A">
            <desc><term>Aporia</term> | <term xml:lang="sa">Neti Neti</term> —
              A passage in which ordinary cognitive effort (seeing, thinking,
              striving) is shown to defeat itself when directed at the object of
              teaching. It does not resolve the block; it uses the block as the
              lesson.</desc>
          </interp>
          
          <interp xml:id="cat-E" n="E">
            <desc><term>Anagnorisis</term> | <term xml:lang="sa">Pratyabhijna</term> —
              A passage where the resolution of the teaching does not come
              directly from the named teacher to the named student in the expected
              sequence. It arrives via an unexpected figure, or it is revealed
              retroactively that the teaching had already been received.</desc>
          </interp>
          
          <interp xml:id="cat-F" n="F">
            <desc><term>Readiness</term> | <term xml:lang="sa">Adhikara</term> —
              Moments where the student's spontaneous action (moral reasoning,
              persistence, or refusal of an offer) constitutes the qualifying
              evidence for receiving the teaching, occurring before and
              independently of the teacher formally naming or testing that
              qualification.</desc>
          </interp>
          
          <interp xml:id="cat-G" n="G">
            <desc><term>Analogy</term> | <term xml:lang="sa">Drstanta</term> —
              A passage that substitutes a sensory, everyday image for an
              abstract or ineffable concept.</desc>
          </interp>
          
          <interp xml:id="cat-H" n="H">
            <desc><term>Formative Labelling</term> —
              A moment where the teacher explicitly and formally names the
              student's category or status (e.g., "one yearning for knowledge"),
              rather than simply praising an action. This confers identity, with
              consequences for what follows.</desc>
          </interp>
          
          <interp xml:id="cat-K" n="K">
            <desc><term>Outcome Statement</term> | <term xml:lang="sa">Phalasruti</term> —
              A passage that states an explicit outcome or stake (what happens to
              one who knows versus one who does not) rather than ending on an
              open or reflective note. Occurs at both the close and, occasionally,
              the opening of a teaching unit.</desc>
          </interp>
          
          <interp xml:id="cat-L" n="L">
            <desc><term>Negative Reference Group</term> —
              A passage in which the student, or the category of the wise, is
              defined in explicit contrast to a named or implied group acting or
              believing incorrectly, rather than through positive description
              alone.</desc>
          </interp>
          
          <interp xml:id="cat-M" n="M">
            <desc><term>Spatial Metaphor for Interiority</term> | <term xml:lang="sa">Guha as fixed locus of Atman</term> —
              An interior cavity, usually the heart, recurring verbatim or
              near-verbatim across multiple teaching units as a fixed location,
              not a one-time comparison.</desc>
          </interp>
          
        </interpGrp>
      </div>

      <div type="footnotes">

        <note xml:id="fn1" n="1" type="translationFlag">
          <p>The phrase "rule of substitution" carries a logical or procedural
          register in English that may not be present in the underlying Sanskrit.
          Olivelle's word choice implies a formal principle of equivalence, but
          it is unclear whether the source text frames this relationship as a
          technical "rule" at all, or whether "substitution" is Olivelle's
          interpretive gloss on a more open-ended correspondence between the
          everyday exclamation ("Ah!") and the divine sphere. This is flagged as
          an open question for review rather than resolved here, since verifying
          it would require consulting the Sanskrit directly rather than working
          from the English translation alone.</p>
        </note>

        <note xml:id="fn2" n="2" type="translationFlag">
          <p>Olivelle renders the proper noun <foreign xml:lang="sa">upanisad</foreign>
          as "hidden connection" throughout this passage rather than leaving the
          term untranslated or using an alternative English rendering such as
          "secret teaching," both of which appear in other published
          translations. This choice is significant beyond ordinary word choice:
          because the term names the genre itself, Olivelle's translation
          functions as an implicit interpretive claim about what an upanisad
          fundamentally is. Every occurrence of the phrase in this passage
          inherits that interpretive framing, which is worth naming explicitly
          rather than treating as a neutral label.</p>
        </note>

        <note xml:id="fn3" n="3" type="taggingNote">
          <p>This passage was initially tested against Category A (Aporia /
          Self-Cancelling Paradox), since its structure of "higher than X is Y"
          statements bears surface resemblance to the regress patterns typical
          of A. On closer testing, the passage held cleanly under Category G's
          decision rule instead: each step in the sequence offers a positive,
          paraphrasable correspondence ("X is like a rung below Y"), rather than
          a self-cancelling formulation, which is the defining test for A. This
          is recorded as a tagging-history note, not a translation flag: no
          sub-category has been created for this ladder-like pattern, and none
          is planned. The instance is simply noted here, alongside its companion
          at Katha 3.10–11, as material for possible future research rather than
          as a formal addition to the ontology.</p>
        </note>

      </div>

    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
